Guide to the Peter Cohen Collection of New York City Snapshots 1891-1981 PR-456
New-York Historical Society
Peter Cohen collection of New York City snapshots
1891-1981
New-York Historical Society
Cohen, Peter
PR-456
approximately 250 photograph(s) in 1 document box (50 folders).
A small collection of amateur, anonymous snapshots of New York City scenes (most in black and white, a handful in color) taken between 1891 and 1981. Along with ubiquitous tourist subjects, such as the Empire State Building and the 1939 World's Fair, the collection includes rare views of early Macy's Thanksgiving Day Parades, which document the first appearances of the balloons "Mickey Mouse" (1934) and "Superman" (1940).
Access Restrictions
This collection may be stored offsite. To arrange to consult it, please go to www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Peter Cohen, 2019 (accession number PPAC-2019-034).
Arrangement
The collection is organized in two series:
Series I. Views of New York City, 1891-1981 & undated
Series II. Views of locations beyond New York City, 1919-1971 & undated
Scope and Contents
The Peter Cohen Collection of New York City Snapshots contains images largely of New York City scenes, and a few of other locations, taken between 1891 and 1981 by anonymous, amateur photographers. Along with popular sites like the Statue of Liberty and Brooklyn Bridge, Central Park and the ubiquitous Manhattan skyline, the collection includes some uncommon street views, such as those taken outside Peter's Italian & American Restaurant at 59 Grove Street, in Greenwich Village, now the site of famed piano bar Marie's Crisis. One rare image from 1949 captures a group of women protesting the "Dividing of Ireland" outside the offices of the British Consulate General, located then in the Empire State Building. (The House of Commons had recently enacted a "New Ireland Bill," enabling the Northern Ireland Parliament to decide the status of its six counties; the demonstrators urged the United Nations to conduct a plebiscite to permit the people to vote on whether or not to join the Republic of Ireland.) Perhaps of most interest are the shots of Macy's Thanksgiving Day Parades from 1933, 1934, 1937, and 1940, which show the first appearances of the balloons "Mickey Mouse" (1934) and "Superman" (1940), among other less-remembered characters such as "Gulliver the Gullible" (1933) and "Morton the Nantucket Sea Monster" (1937). Also present are views of people posed on ferries or rooftops, or in various places throughout the city. A small number of images from locations beyond New York City (only a few of which are identifiable) rounds out the collection. Except for a handful in color, all the photographs in this collection are in black and white.
Separated Materials
The donation of this collection included a handful of cabinet card portraits, about 30 postcards, and 2 stereographs, all of which have been removed to the New-York Historical Society Library's Portrait File (PR-52), Postcard File (PR-54), and Stereograph File (PR-65).
Black-and-white photographs.; Color photographs.; Snapshots.; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs.; Manhattan (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs.; Queens (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs.; Staten Island (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs.; Statue of Liberty National Monument (N.Y. and N.J.); Bridges -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs.; Buildings -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs.; Monuments -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs.; Parades -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs.; Parks -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs.; Streets -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs.; Thanksgiving Day.; Theaters -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs.; New York World's Fair (1939-1940: New York, N.Y.) [111] -- Photographs.
- Series I. Views of New York City, 1891-1981 & undated
  - Bridges [16 images], 1925-1947 & undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    • Brooklyn Bridge [9 images], undated
    • George Washington Bridge [3 images], 1941 October & undated
    • Hell Gate Bridge [1 image], undated
    • Manhattan Bridge [1 image], 1925 August 29
    • Marine Parkway Bridge [1 image], 1947 May
    • Unidentified NYC-area bridge under construction [1 image], undated
  - Brooklyn — Brooklyn Heights [2 images], 1948 May (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Aerial views of taken from the roof of the Squibb Plant, 25–30 Columbia Heights.
  - Brooklyn — Coney Island [5 images (1 color)], 1930 & undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    • Bather at Sea Gate, undated
    • Cyclone, undated
    • Man swimming with campanile of Our Lady of Solace in background, 1930
    • Parachute Jump [2 images (1 color)], undated
  - Manhattan — Buildings — 1 New York Plaza [1 image (color)], undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Manhattan — Buildings — Chrysler Building (405 Lexington Avenue) [1 image], undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Manhattan — Buildings — Empire State Building (350 Fifth Avenue) [4 images], 1946 November 22 & undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Manhattan — Buildings — Flatiron Building [3 images (1 color)], 1919 & undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Manhattan — Buildings — Lord & Taylor (424-434 Fifth Avenue) [1 image], 1943 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Manhattan — Buildings — New York Stock Exchange (18 Broad Street) [1 image], undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Manhattan — Buildings — Panhellenic Tower, a.k.a. Beekman Tower (1-7 Mitchell Place) [1 image], undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Manhattan — Buildings — Pennsylvania Station [1 image], undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Manhattan — Buildings — Rockefeller Center [12 images (1 color)], 1937-1966 & undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Manhattan — Buildings — Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum (1071 Fifth Avenue) [1 image (color)], 1965 August (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Manhattan — Buildings — United Nations Secretariat Building [2 images], 1957 August 8 & undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Manhattan — Buildings — Woolworth Building (233 Broadway) [6 images], 1926 June & undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Manhattan — Buildings — World Trade Center [2 images (color)], undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Manhattan — Monuments and statues [21 images (1 color)], 1942, 1945 & undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    • Statue of Liberty [17 images (1 color)], 1942, 1945 December 3 & undated
    • George Washington equestrian statue, Union Square [1 image], undated
    • Washington Arch [3 images], undated
  - Manhattan — Parks [12 images (4 color)], 1918-1951 & undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    • Battery Park [3 images] (1935 April 20 & undated) and South Ferry [1] (1948 August)
    • Central Park [7 images (4 color)] (1946, 1951 & undated)
    • Madison Square [1 image] (1918 November 11, Armistice Day)
  - Manhattan — Skyline [6 images], 1932, 1933, 1952 & undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Includes aerial views taken from the tops of the RCA Building (1932), 580 Fifth Avenue (1933), the Empire State Building (July 1952), and the Woolworth Building (undated).
  - Manhattan — Streets — Broadway [2 images (1 color)], 1947, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    • Looking north from Dey Street, 1947
    • Looking south from West 96th Street (color; shows telephone booth and red & blue mailbox), 1964 April
  - Manhattan — Streets — Christopher Street [1 image], undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    View includes St. Veronica Church, 153 Christopher Street.
  - Manhattan — Streets — Cooper Square [1 image], circa 1964 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    View of 61–71 Cooper Square between East 7th Street and St. Mark's Place.
  - Manhattan — Streets — Grove Street [2 images], [before 1937] (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Views outside Peter's Italian & American Restaurant, 59 Grove Street, future site of Marie's Crisis; the building stands on the site where Thomas Paine died in 1809.
  - Manhattan — Streets — Riverside Drive [1 image], 1919 April 27 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    View of the intersection of Riverside Drive and West 135th Street, wth a battleship passing in the Hudson River.
  - Manhattan — Streets — Wall Street [1 image (color)], 1981 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Manhattan — Streets — Washington Square North [1 image], undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Manhattan — Streets — West 33rd Street [2 images], undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
    • South side, outside Penn Station, looking east to Empire State Building
    • Looking east to Empire State Building from just west of the bridge connecting Gimbels and Saks stores over West 33rd (demolished 1966)
  - Manhattan — Streets — West 34th Street [1 image], 1933 January 1 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Looking east to Empire State Building from between Eighth and Ninth Avenues.
  - Manhattan — Streets — Unidentified [4 images (3 color)], undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Manhattan — Theaters & entertainment venues [3 images], 1935, 1941 & undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
    • Hippodrome (1120 Sixth Avenue), 1935
    • Madison Square Garden (3rd site; Eighth Avenue between West 49th & 50th Streets), 1941 January
    • Rialto Theatre (1481 Broadway), undated
  - Manhattan — Waterfront [11 images (1 color)], 1933, 1958, 1970 & undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Views of piers, ferries, ships, and New York Harbor.
  - Parades & protests — May Day / Communist Parade [2 images], 1935 May 1 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Parades & protests — V-J Day, Wall Street [4 images], [1945] (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Parades & protests — "Dividing of Ireland" [1 image], [1949 May 31] (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Women holding placards outside the British Consulate General's office in the Empire State Building. For a description, see "100 Pickets Protest 'Dividing' of Ireland," New York Times, June 1, 1949, p. 36, col. 3 (copy included in folder).
  - Parades & protests — Macy's Thanksgiving Day Parade, 1933 [3 images], 1933 November 30 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Includes views of the balloons "Fritz the Dachshund" and "Gulliver the Gullible." The latter debuted in 1933.
  - Parades & protests — Macy's Thanksgiving Day Parade, 1934 [6 images], 1934 November 29 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Includes views of the balloons "Colicky Kid," "Eddie Cantor," "Little Pig," and "Mickey Mouse." The last three debuted in 1934.
  - Parades & protests — Macy's Thanksgiving Day Parade, 1937 [5 images], 1937 November 25 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Includes views of the balloons "Morton the Nantucket Sea Monster" and "Officer SOS 13," both of which debuted in 1937.
  - Parades & protests — Macy's Thanksgiving Day Parade, 1940 [15 images], 1940 November 21 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Includes views of the balloons "Uncle Sam," "Santa Claus," and "Superman." The latter debuted in 1940.
    [Note the date discrepancy in the captions on these photographs, some of which read "Nov. 21, 1940," and some of which read "Nov. 25, 1940." Thanksgiving 1940 actually fell on November 21. The holiday fell on November 25 in 1937 and in 1943 (there was no parade in 1943 due to U.S. involvement in World War II). None of the three balloons mentioned above appeared before 1938. This version of "Uncle Sam" appeared in 1938-1940; "Santa Claus" appeared in 1939-1941; and this version of "Superman" appeared only in 1940. Thus the caption date of "Nov. 21, 1940" is likely correct.]
  - People — On ferries [6 images], 1912, 1939, 1958 & undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - People — On rooftops [7 images], 1891, 1931, 1935 & undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - People — Posed throughout New York City [21 images (4 color)], 1943 & undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Queens — 1939 World's Fair [21 images], 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    Includes views of the night fountain and fireworks displays.
  - Queens — Rockaway [5 images], 1915, 1939, 1944, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Staten Island — Small boy holding "Staten Island" pennant [1 image], undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
    Taken near a street sign for Martling Avenue.
- Series II. Views of locations beyond New York City, 1919-1971 & undated
  - California — San Francisco — Bay Bridge [1 image], undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - New Jersey — Atlantic City [1 image], 1927 July (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - New York State — Nassau County — Jones Beach [3 images], 1935-1942 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    • Jones Beach Water Tower [1 image], 1935 July 29
    • Beachgoers [2 images], 1938, 1942
  - New York State — Unidentified locations [11 images], 1919 September (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Parades & protests — Unidentified locations [6 images (1 color)], circa 1926-1971 & undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
    Includes a view of an early Nazi rally.
  - Miscellaneous [6 images (1 color)], undated (Box 1, Folder 50)